都市[とし]:town/city/municipal, 伝説[でんせつ]:tradition/legend/folklore, 電脳[でんのう]:computer|cyberbrain/digital brain, ペット:pet, ペット:polyethylene terephthalate/PET
（ヤサコ）都市伝説によると
電脳ペットは死んだあと―
According to urban legends,
after they die, cyberpets go live somewhere else.
場所[ばしょ]:place|room|basho, 移り住む[うつりすむ]:to change one's place of residence/to migrate/to move
ある場所に移り住むそうです
患者[かんじゃ]:(a) patient, ナンバー:number
（メガばあ）４４２３は
イサコの患者ナンバーじゃ
4-4-2-3 is Isako's patient number!
治療[ちりょう, じりょう]:medical treatment/cure, 設置[せっち]:establishment/institution|installation (of a machine or equipment)
彼女の治療のために
設置された―
The experimental Space created for Isako's cybercure,
実験[じっけん]:experiment, 医療[いりょう]:medical care/medical treatment, 空間[くうかん]:space/room/airspace, 空間[あきま]:vacancy/room for rent or lease
実験医療空間
４４２３が
4-4-2-3, is the original model for "the other side."
あっち:that way (direction distant from both speaker and listener)/over there|that one (something physically distant from both speaker and listener, or something not visible but known by both speaker and listener), 原型[げんけい]:prototype/model/pattern
あっちの原型なのじゃ
それに
信彦(のぶひこ)が死んだのは
Moreover, Nobuhiko didn't die because Isako made a wish to Michiko.
願う[ねがう]:to desire|to beg|to have something done for oneself
イサコがミチコに
願ったからではない
どういう:somehow/how/in what way
（オバちゃん）どういうこと？
What do you mean?
交通事故[こうつうじこ]:traffic accident, 直後[ちょくご]:immediately following, すでに:already/too late
（メガばあ）信彦は交通事故の直後
すでに死んでおったのじゃ
Nobuhiko had already died in the car accident!
事故[じこ, ことゆえ]:accident/incident|circumstances, かろうじて:barely/narrowly/just manage to do something, 目覚める[めざめる]:to wake up|to awaken to (instinct, ability, perception, etc.)|to come to one's senses
事故のあと かろうじて
目覚めた彼女は
When she finally awakened after the accident,
兄[あに]:elder brother/older brother, 兄[けい]:elder brother|pronoun or suffix used in reference to an older brother figure/Mister, 失う[うしなう]:to lose/to part with, 再び[ふたたび]:again/once more/a second time, 意識[いしき]:consciousness|awareness|mano-vijnana (mental consciousness, cognizer of sensory information), 閉ざす[とざす, さす]:to shut/to close|to plunge (in grief)
兄を失ったことを知って
再び意識を閉ざした
she learned of her brother's death and lost consciousness once again.
傷[きず, キズ]:wound|chip|flaw||, 癒やす[いやす]:to heal/to cure
その心の傷を
癒やすために―
In order to relieve her broken heart, a Space was created.
作る[つくる]:to make|to prepare (food)|to raise||, 空間[くうかん]:space/room/airspace, 空間[あきま]:vacancy/room for rent or lease
作られた空間
埋める[うずめる]:to cover/to bury (e.g. one's face in hands)|to fill (completely), 埋める[うめる]:to bury (e.g. in the ground)|to fill up (e.g. audience fills a hall)|to plug (a gap)||, イマーゴ:imago, 通ずる[つうずる]:to be open (to traffic)|to flow (liquid, current)|to be understood||
心を埋めるものを
イマーゴを通じて―
A Space that uses the Imago to create cybersubstances
電脳[でんのう]:computer|cyberbrain/digital brain, 物質[ぶっしつ]:material/substance|matter, 形[かたち, よう]:form/shape|visage, 形[かた, がた]:shape|collateral|obverse of an old "zeni" coin, 生み出す[うみだす]:to create|to invent|to give birth to, 空間[くうかん]:space/room/airspace, 空間[あきま]:vacancy/room for rent or lease
電脳物質の形で
生み出す空間
that fill the gap in a person's heart.
失う[うしなう]:to lose/to part with, 兄[あに]:elder brother/older brother, 兄[けい]:elder brother|pronoun or suffix used in reference to an older brother figure/Mister, 姿[すがた]:figure|appearance|state||
そう
失った兄の姿までも…
Right, even including the illusion of a dead brother.
原因[げんいん]:cause/origin/source, 変質[へんしつ]:alteration (of character or essence)/change in quality/transformation
しかし なんらかの
原因で変質し
However, for some reason, the Space degenerated...
ついに:finally/at last|in the end, 停止[ていし, ちょうじ]:suspension/interruption|suspension of music, dance, etc. as a sign of mourning for a prominent person
ついには停止した
In the end, it ceased to exist,
治療[ちりょう, じりょう]:medical treatment/cure
治療中の天沢(あまさわ)勇子(ゆうこ)と―
along with Amasawa, who was still in treatment,
生み出す[うみだす]:to create|to invent|to give birth to, 世界[せかい]:the world|sphere|renowned|
彼女の生み出した
心の世界とともに
and the world born inside her heart.
医師[いし]:doctor/physician, 医師[くすし, くすりし]:doctor, 手術[しゅじゅつ]:(surgical) operation/procedure
じゃあ 小此木(おこのぎ)医師が
手術したっていうのは…
So, the procedure that Dr. Okonogi created...
唯一[ゆいいつ, ゆいつ]:only/sole/unique, 電脳[でんのう]:computer|cyberbrain/digital brain, コイル:coil, システム:system
（メガばあ）そう 唯一
電脳コイルシステムを知るおじじが
Exactly, only Grandpa knew about the Dennou Coil system.
救う[すくう]:to rescue from/to help out of/to save, キャリア:career, 意識[いしき]:consciousness|awareness|mano-vijnana (mental consciousness, cognizer of sensory information), 分離[ぶんり]:separation/partition/detachment
彼女を救うために
ヌル･キャリアで意識を分離させ
So, in order to save her,
he split his own consciousness,
医療[いりょう]:medical care/medical treatment, 空間[くうかん]:space/room/airspace, 空間[あきま]:vacancy/room for rent or lease, 入り込む[はいりこむ, いりこむ]:to go into/to come into|to become complicated
医療空間に入り込んだのじゃ
and entered the healing Space via the Null Carrier.
戻る[もどる]:to turn back (e.g. half-way)|to return|to recover (e.g. something lost)|, 戻る[もとる]:to go against/to act contrary to/to deviate from
そして 彼女は戻ってきた
And then she came back.
じゃが:potato (Solanum tuberosum)
じゃが…
However...
先生[せんせい, せんじょう]:teacher|with names of teachers, etc. as an honorific|previous existence, 先生[シーサン]:boy, 戻る[もどる]:to turn back (e.g. half-way)|to return|to recover (e.g. something lost)|, 戻る[もとる]:to go against/to act contrary to/to deviate from
（イサコの叔父）小此木先生は
そのまま戻られませんでした
Dr. Okonogi never came back.
先生[せんせい, せんじょう]:teacher|with names of teachers, etc. as an honorific|previous existence, 先生[シーサン]:boy, 救う[すくう]:to rescue from/to help out of/to save, くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one
先生が勇子を救ってくだすった
He saved Yuko,
ご自身[ごじしん]:himself/yourself/herself, 体[からだ]:body|torso|build||, 体[たい]:body|shape|substance||, 省みる[かえりみる]:to look back (e.g. over shoulder or at the past)|to reflect on the past|to reflect on oneself|
ご自身の体を省みずに…
at the cost of his own life.
資料[しりょう]:materials/data/document, イマーゴ:imago, 大人[おとな, だいにん]:adult, 大人[たいじん]:man of substance or virtue|giant|adult, うまい:skillful/skilful|delicious, 適合[てきごう]:conformity/compatibility/adaptability
（メガばあ）
資料によるとイマーゴは
大人にはうまく適合せん
According to the data, adults aren't very compatible with the Imago.
負荷[ふか]:burden/load (e.g. cpu time, electricity, etc.), かかる:to span/to bridge/to cross, かかる:to take (a resource, e.g. time or money)|to hang, 体[からだ]:body|torso|build||, 体[たい]:body|shape|substance||
負荷がかかった
おじじの体は―
Grandpa's body, already badly strained,
分離[ぶんり]:separation/partition/detachment, 尽きる[つきる]:to be used up/to be run out/to be exhausted, しまう:to finish/to stop|to close (a business, etc.)
分離しただけで
力尽きてしもうた
exhausted its strength while still split.
先[さき]:previous|point (e.g. pencil)|head (of a line)||, 先[せん]:former/previous|first move (in go, shogi, etc.), 覚える[おぼえる]:to memorize|to learn|to feel|
（ヤサコ）
ここから先は覚えてないわ
I don't remember what happened after that.
実験[じっけん]:experiment, 空間[くうかん]:space/room/airspace, 空間[あきま]:vacancy/room for rent or lease, 知れる[しれる]:to become known|to be known|to obviously not amount to much||
（メガばあ）実験空間は人知れず
The experimental Space changed over time into an abnormal Space called "the other side."
あっち:that way (direction distant from both speaker and listener)/over there|that one (something physically distant from both speaker and listener, or something not visible but known by both speaker and listener), 呼ぶ[よぶ]:to call out (to)|to summon (a doctor, etc.)|to invite||, 異[い]:difference (of opinion)|strange|different, 異[こと, け]:difference (from one another)/different thing|unusual, 空間[くうかん]:space/room/airspace, 空間[あきま]:vacancy/room for rent or lease, 変容[へんよう]:change in appearance/transformation, 遂げる[とげる]:to accomplish/to achieve|to arrive at (a certain outcome)
あっちと呼ばれる
異空間に変容を遂げていった
4-4...
2-3.
その後[そのあと, そのご]:after that/afterwards/thereafter, しばらく:little while/short while|a while, 意識[いしき]:consciousness|awareness|mano-vijnana (mental consciousness, cognizer of sensory information)
その後 しばらく
おじじの意識は―
Brother?
Ever since then, I guess Grandpa's consciousness has wandered around "the other side"...
あっち:that way (direction distant from both speaker and listener)/over there|that one (something physically distant from both speaker and listener, or something not visible but known by both speaker and listener), さまよう:to loiter/to putter/to prowl
あっちを
さまよっていたことじゃろう
I'm looking for 4-4-2-3.
捜し求める[さがしもとめる]:to search for/to seek for/to look for
４４２３ 天沢勇子を捜し求めてな
looking for 4-4-2-3, alias Yuko Okonogi.
（ヌル）私ハ 小此木
I'm...
Okonogi.
同じ[おなじ, おんなじ]:same/identical|(usu. part of a 'nara' conditional) anyway
（幼少のヤサコ）私と同じ名前だ
That's the same as my family name.
Yu... ko?
おじじ？
Grandpa!
優子
Yu... ko.
優子じゃないか！
Now that's my Yuko!
おじじ！　おじじだ～！
Grandpa!
It's Grandpa!
ぽっくり:girl's lacquered wooden geta|wooden footwear/clogs, ぽっくり:(dying) suddenly|(breaking) brittly/with a snap
（幼少のヤサコ）
おじじは死んだんだよ ぽっくり
But Grandpa's dead.
Suddenly.
思い出す[おもいだす]:to recall/to remember/to recollect
ほおっ 思い出した
Oh! I remember!
こないだ:the other day/lately/recently
わしは こないだ死んだんじゃ
I died the other day!
あっち:that way (direction distant from both speaker and listener)/over there|that one (something physically distant from both speaker and listener, or something not visible but known by both speaker and listener)
私 あっちで
おじじと会ってたんだ
So on "the other side," I met Grandpa!
（幼少のヤサコ）
デンスケについてきたら
ここに来ちゃったの
I was following Densuke, and ended up here.
（おじじ）そうか
I see.
That's because Densuke was part of this treatment area.
治療[ちりょう, じりょう]:medical treatment/cure, 施設[しせつ]:institution/establishment|(army) engineer, 一部[いちぶ]:one part/one portion|one copy (e.g. of a document)
デンスケも
この治療施設の一部だったからな
えっ？　そうだったんだ
So that's how things were!
さっき:some time ago/just now, さっき:thirst for blood/bloodlust/determination to kill
さっき４４２３に会ったよ
You know, I just met 4-4-2-3.
女の子[おんなのこ, おんなのコ]:girl/daughter|young woman, 女の子[めのこ]:woman/girl
でも女の子じゃなかった
But he wasn't a girl.
暗い[くらい]:dark|dark (in colour)|depressed||, 消える[きえる]:to go out/to vanish/to disappear
それに暗くなって消えちゃったの
And then, it became dark and he disappeared.
そうか どこにいるか分かるかい？
Really?
Any clue about where he might be?
Nope.
まあええ
Oh, whatever.
起こる[おこる]:to occur/to happen
さあ もうこんなことが
起こらんように―
I gotta put a lock on to make sure things like this don't happen anymore.
鍵をかける[かぎをかける, カギをかける]:to lock
鍵をかけねばな
かける:to hang (e.g. picture)/to hoist (e.g. sail)|to sit, かける:to run (race, esp. horse)/to dash|to gallop (one's horse), しまう:to finish/to stop|to close (a business, etc.)
かける前に死んでしまったんじゃ
I died before I could lock it.
帰り道[かえりみち]:the way back or home/return trip
（おじじ）
帰り道はデンスケが知っておる
Densuke knows the way back.
孫[まご]:grandchild, ボディーガード:bodyguard
（おじじ）さあ デンスケ
孫のボディーガードになっておくれ
Come on, Densuke,
be my granddaughter's bodyguard for a while.
（おじじ）さあ 行くんだ
Go on then.
おじじ？
Grandpa?
（おじじ）さあ デンスケとお行き
Go on, go with Densuke.
首輪[くびわ]:(animal) collar|necklace/choker, かける:to hang (e.g. picture)/to hoist (e.g. sail)|to sit, かける:to run (race, esp. horse)/to dash|to gallop (one's horse), 全部[ぜんぶ]:all/entire/whole, 忘れる[わすれる]:to forget/to leave carelessly/to be forgetful of
そして 首輪をかけて
全部 忘れるんだ
And then put the collar on him and forget about all this.
一緒[いっしょ]:together|at the same time|same, 帰る[かえる]:to return|to leave|to get home
おじじ 一緒に帰ろう！
Grandpa! Let's go back together!
（おじじ）お行き
Go.
迎える[むかえる]:to go out to meet|to receive|to accept (e.g. as a member of a group or family)||
わしは迎えに行かねばならん子が
いるんじゃよ
I must go and meet a certain child.
おじじ！
Grandpa!
おじじ…
Grandpa.
さっき:some time ago/just now, さっき:thirst for blood/bloodlust/determination to kill
あなた さっきの？
You're... the one from just now?
Haraken!
ハラケン！
イリーガル:illegal
イリーガル… じゃない
An Illegal?
No, it's not.
ハッ… デンスケ？
Densuke?
ワン！
デンスケ！
Densuke!
ク～ン…
デンスケ…
Densuke...
I missed you!
会いたかった
You're warm!
あったかい:warm/mild/genial
あったかい　フフ フフフ…
Densuke's fur is so...
毛並み[けなみ]:lie of a (dog's) hair|type|lineage, フサフサ:in tufts/tufty/bushy
デンスケの毛並み
フサフサだったんだね
fluffy.
You're warm.
あったかい:warm/mild/genial
あったかい
あっ デンスケ？
Densuke?
デンスケ…
Densuke...
Is this our farewell?
別れ[わかれ]:parting/separation/farewell
お別れなの？
ク～ン…
Densuke!
ありがとう:Thank you/Thanks
デンスケ ありがとう！
Thank you!
Really,
今まで[いままで]:until now/so far/up to the present, ありがとう:Thank you/Thanks
今まで本当にありがとう
thank you for everything.
Goodbye...
さようなら:good-bye
さようなら デンスケ
Densuke.
Yasako!
（ハラケン）ヤサコ！
（ヤサコ）ハッ…
Yasako!
Aunty, Yasako is...
オバちゃん ヤサコが…
Yasako.
（オバちゃん）ヤサコ！
Aunty.
オバちゃん ハラケン…
Haraken.
But how could you...
一体[いったい]:...the heck (e.g. "what the heck?")|one object|one form||
一体どうやって？
Densuke
案内[あんない]:information/guidance|to guide
デンスケが案内してくれたの
guided me.
Densuke?
デンスケが？
He was all black, but...
真っ黒[まっくろ]:pitch black, 毛並み[けなみ]:lie of a (dog's) hair|type|lineage
真っ黒になってたけど
毛並みがフカフカだったよ
his fur was soft and fluffy!
I was able to say goodbye.
さよなら:good-bye, 言える[いえる]:to be possible to say/to be able to say
さよならが言えたよ
I won't allow it.
許す[ゆるす]:to permit|to exempt (from fine)|to confide in|
（ミチコ）許さない
Amasawa...
天沢さん…
大黒[だいこく]:god of wealth|monk's wife, 市[いち]:market/fair, 市[し]:city, 連れる[つれる]:to lead/to take (a person)
ハッ… 大黒市(だいこくし)に連れてって！
Take me to Daikoku City!
Pronto!
今すぐ！
What about her cyberbody?
電脳[でんのう]:computer|cyberbrain/digital brain, 体[からだ]:body|torso|build||, 体[たい]:body|shape|substance||
電脳体は？
Not yet!
一部[いちぶ]:one part/one portion|one copy (e.g. of a document), 戻る[もどる]:to turn back (e.g. half-way)|to return|to recover (e.g. something lost)|, 戻る[もとる]:to go against/to act contrary to/to deviate from, 始める[はじめる]:to start|to open (e.g. a store)|to start ...
まだじゃ… しかし
なぜか一部が戻り始めておる
But a part has mysteriously started to come back!
So, will Amasawa...
（ヤサコ）じゃあ 天沢さんは？
I don't know yet.
（メガばあ）まだ分からん
Then what can we do?
（オバちゃん）
じゃあ どうするのよ？
（メガばあ）うむ…
こんなこともあろうかと思って
I thought something like this could happen.
I'm gonna use my ace in the hole.
切り札[きりふだ]:trump card|ace up one's sleeve/secret weapon, 連絡[れんらく]:to contact|contacting|connection|, 済み[ずみ, すみ]:arranged/taken care of/settled
切り札に連絡済みじゃ
Ace in the hole?
切り札[きりふだ]:trump card|ace up one's sleeve/secret weapon
切り札？
バイク:motorcycle/motorbike
げっ！　バ… バイクが
Vehicle Removed for Parking Violation
M-My motorbike!
Geez!
しまう:to finish/to stop|to close (a business, etc.)
しまった…
Get in!
乗る[のる]:to get on (train, plane, bus, ship, etc.)|to get on (e.g. a footstool)|to reach||
（一郎(いちろう)）乗るんだ
Supervisor?
室長[しつちょう]:section chief/laboratory manager/office head
室長？
Supervisor,
室長[しつちょう]:section chief/laboratory manager/office head, ことになる:it has been decided (so) that/it has been arranged (so) that|it is the result (of)
（オバちゃん）室長
こんなことになってすみません
I'm sorry about all this.
But...
娘[じょう]:unmarried woman|Miss|-ess, 娘[むすめ]:(my) daughter|girl (i.e. a young, unmarried woman), 決して[けっして, けして]:never/by no means/not in the least
でも 娘さんの
やろうとしていることは決して…
what your daughter wanted to do is in no way...
In the cyberpocket in back, you'll find a metatag.
後部[こうぶ]:rear/stern, 電脳[でんのう]:computer|cyberbrain/digital brain, ポシェット:pochette/pouch (usu. hung from the shoulder by a long cord), メタタグ:META tag
（一郎）後部の電脳ポシェットに
メタタグが入っている
A metatag?
メタタグ:META tag
メタタグ？
It's this one...
（ハラケン）これだ
That's a Coil Tag.
コイルタグだ！
ちょ… なんで こんなもの？
Why do you have this?
It's not an original.
本物[ほんもの]:genuine article/real thing/real deal, 技術[ぎじゅつ]:technology|technique|art, 再現[さいげん]:reappearance/reproduction/return
（一郎）本物じゃない
僕の技術では再現できなかった
I wasn't able to reproduce it with my technique,
but it will work as a makeshift solution.
対症療法[たいしょうりょうほう]:symptomatic therapy/makeshift solution, くらい:dark/gloomy|dark (in colour), くらい:approximately/about|to (about) the extent that
でも 対症療法くらいにはなる
Dad?
お父さん[おとうさん, おとっさん]:father/dad/papa
お… お父さん？
Yuko, I'm sorry I couldn't be by your side at a moment like this.
近く[ちかく]:near|nearly (e.g. "it took nearly one year")|shortly
優子 こんなときに
近くにいてやれなくてすまなかった
Supervisor... don't tell me you are...
室長[しつちょう]:section chief/laboratory manager/office head, まさか:by no means/never!|something unexpected
室長 あんた まさか…
I'm member number one.
会員[かいいん]:member/the membership, 番号[ばんごう]:number/series of digits, 番[ばん]:number (in a series)|(one's) turn|watch|, 番[つがい]:(one) pair (e.g. of birds)/brace|joint
会員番号１番だ
コイル:coil, 探偵[たんてい]:detective/sleuth/investigator, 局[きょく]:bureau|office (e.g. post, telephone)|affair|, 局[つぼね]:court lady|separate room in a palace (esp. for a lady) (Heian period)|room for a very low class prostitute|, バッジ:badge
（ハラケン･オバちゃん）
あっ コイル探偵局のバッジ！
Ah, the Coil Investigation badge!
My mom...
おふくろ:one's mother, いろいろ:various|various colors (colours), 弱み[よわみ]:(a) weakness/shortcoming/failing, 握る[にぎる]:to clasp|to make (nigirizushi, rice ball, etc.)|to seize (power, etc.)
（一郎）おふくろには
いろいろ弱みを握られていてな
forced me into it with threats.
I knew it had to be a trick like that!
やはり:too/also|still, 手口[てぐち]:modus operandi/criminal technique/trick
やはり その手口か
Not only that, you should know that for the last six months,
それだけじゃない
実[じつ, じち]:truth|sincerity|content|, 実[み]:fruit|seed|(in broth) pieces of meat, vegetable, etc.|, 半年[はんとし, はんねん]:half year, 本社[ほんしゃ, ほんじゃ]:head office|main shrine|this company, 要請[ようせい]:appeal/call for something|axiom
実は半年ほど前から
メガマス本社の要請で―
at the request of the Megamass head office, I've been helping out with an internal audit.
内部監査[ないぶかんさ]:internal audit, 手伝う[てつだう]:to help/to assist|to contribute to
内部監査を手伝っていたんだ
一体[いったい]:...the heck (e.g. "what the heck?")|one object|one form||, リンク:link/directory entry
（メガばあ）んん… それにしても
一体 どこからリンクが？
But still, I wonder just where this link is...
（モジョ）モジョ
You fiends!
曲者[くせもの]:ruffian|peculiar person|tricky thing||
曲者！
うっ… この！
Take this!
リンク:link/directory entry
うぬっ！　リンクが…
The link is...
This is an old-school encode!
古流[こりゅう]:old manners/old style/old school (of art), 暗号[あんごう]:code/password/cipher
これは古流の暗号か？
Even inside Megamass, there is a faction of former Coil employees.
内部[ないぶ]:interior/inside/internal, 旧[きゅう]:ex-/former/old, 旧[ふる]:used item/secondhand item|old, つながる:to be tied together/to be connected to|to lead to, 一派[いっぱ]:school/sect/party
（一郎）メガマス内部にも
旧コイルスとつながった一派がいる
They have someone working on recovering lost Coil techniques.
動かす[うごかす]:to move|to inspire|to change||
彼らはある男を動かして
失う[うしなう]:to lose/to part with, 技術[ぎじゅつ]:technology|technique|art, 手に入れる[てにいれる]:to obtain/to procure
失われたコイルスの技術を
手に入れようとしている
And who on earth is this person?
一体[いったい]:...the heck (e.g. "what the heck?")|one object|one form||, 何者[なにもの]:who/what kind of person
（オバちゃん）
それは 一体 何者なの？
Do you know the name of Coil's now missing master engineer?
失踪[しっそう]:absconding/disappearance, 主任[しゅにん]:person in charge/senior staff/manager, 技師[ぎし]:engineer/technician
失踪したコイルス主任技師の
名前を知っているか？
癖[くせ, へき]:habit (often a bad habit, i.e. vice)|peculiarity|crease, 暗号[あんごう]:code/password/cipher, 組む[くむ]:to cross (legs or arms)|to put together|to braid||, 方[かた]:direction|person|method of||, 方[ほう]:direction|side (of an argument, etc.)|type||
うむ この癖 この暗号の組み方…
This style...
This way of compiling the encode...
Maybe it's
会員[かいいん]:member/the membership, 番号[ばんごう]:number/series of digits, 番[ばん]:number (in a series)|(one's) turn|watch|, 番[つがい]:(one) pair (e.g. of birds)/brace|joint
もしや 会員番号３番 猫目(ねこめ)か？
member number three,
Nekome?!
The engineer's name was...
技師[ぎし]:engineer/technician
（一郎）その技師の名は猫目
Nekome.
What?
なんですって？
Sosuke Nekome is the son of the deceased engineer.
猫[ねこ, ネコ]:cat|shamisen|geisha||, 猫[ねこま]:cat, 失踪[しっそう]:absconding/disappearance, 技師[ぎし]:engineer/technician, 息子[むすこ, そく]:son|penis
猫目宗助(そうすけ)は
失踪した技師の息子だ
Long time no see, Mega-baa.
久しぶり[ひさしぶり]:a long time (since the last time)/it's been a while (since I last saw, mailed, etc., you)
（猫目）お久しぶりです メガばあ
Sosuke...
お主[おぬし]:you (when referring to one's equals or inferiors), たくらむ:to scheme/to plan/to play a trick
宗助 お主 何をたくらんでおる？
What'cha plotting?!
I'm not plotting anything.
たくらむ:to scheme/to plan/to play a trick
（猫目）何もたくらんでなどいない
My goal is the same as before.
目標[めじるし]:mark/sign/landmark, 目標[もくひょう]:mark/objective/target, 頃[ころ, ごろ]:(approximate) time|suitable time (or condition)|time of year, 頃[けい]:qing (Chinese unit of land area equal to 100 mu), 同じ[おなじ, おんなじ]:same/identical|(usu. part of a 'nara' conditional) anyway
僕の目標は あの頃と同じだ
I remembered everything.
全て[すべて]:everything/all|entirely, 思い出す[おもいだす]:to recall/to remember/to recollect, たわい:sanity/soundness of mind|drunkenness
全て思い出したわい
You wanna get revenge against Megamass!
復讐[ふくしゅう]:revenge, 気[き]:spirit|nature|motivation||, 気[げ]:seeming/giving the appearance of/giving one the feeling of
メガマスに復讐(ふくしゅう)する気なのじゃな？
Yeah,
報い[むくい]:reward/recompense/return, 受ける[うける, ウケる]:to receive|to catch (e.g. a ball)|to be struck by (wind, waves, sunlight, etc.)||, させる:to make (someone) do|to allow (someone) to, させる:(usu. followed by a negative form) worth special consideration
ああ 報いを受けさせてやる
I'll make them pay through the nose.
お主[おぬし]:you (when referring to one's equals or inferiors), 玉子[たまご]:eggs|hen egg|(an expert) in the making|, そそのかす:to instigate/to tempt, ばかり:only/merely|approximately
４年前も お主が
玉子(たまこ)をそそのかしたばかりに…
I remembered that four years ago, it was all your fault. You put Tamako up to it.
止める[とめる]:to stop|to park|to prevent||, 止める[やめる]:to stop (an activity)/to cease|to cancel
わしが止めなければ―
If I hadn't stopped her,
玉子[たまご]:eggs|hen egg|(an expert) in the making|, あっち:that way (direction distant from both speaker and listener)/over there|that one (something physically distant from both speaker and listener, or something not visible but known by both speaker and listener), しれる:to become known/to come to light|to be known
玉子があっちに行っていたの
かもしれぬのじゃぞ！
she would've ended up on "the other side"!
旧[きゅう]:ex-/former/old, 旧[ふる]:used item/secondhand item|old, 一派[いっぱ]:school/sect/party, 組む[くむ]:to cross (legs or arms)|to put together|to braid||
（一郎）
彼は旧コイルス一派と組んで
He joined the faction of former Coil personnel,
イマーゴ:imago, 軸[じく]:axis|center|stalk|, 本社[ほんしゃ, ほんじゃ]:head office|main shrine|this company, 脅す[おどす]:to threaten/to menace/to bully, 気[き]:spirit|nature|motivation||, 気[げ]:seeming/giving the appearance of/giving one the feeling of
イマーゴを軸に
本社を脅す気だったんだろう
probably intending to threaten the head office about the Imago.
まさか:by no means/never!|something unexpected, 事故[じこ, ことゆえ]:accident/incident|circumstances
（オバちゃん）
まさか カンナの事故も？
Do you mean that Kanna's accident also...
原因[げんいん]:cause/origin/source, イマーゴ:imago, 古い[ふるい]:old (not person)/aged/ancient, 空間[くうかん]:space/room/airspace, 空間[あきま]:vacancy/room for rent or lease, 起こる[おこる]:to occur/to happen
いや 原因は イマーゴと
古い空間によって起こった―
Nope, that was a navi malfunction caused by the Imago and obsolete Space.
誤動作[ごどうさ]:malfunction
ナビの誤動作だ
Thanks to Ken'ichi's data, we managed to prove it.
データ:data/datum, 裏付ける[うらづける]:to support/to endorse/to substantiate
研一(けんいち)君のデータが
それを裏付けたよ
ホント:truth/reality/actuality
ホントですか？
Really?
本社[ほんしゃ, ほんじゃ]:head office|main shrine|this company, 不具合[ふぐあい]:flaw/defect|inconvenient, 公表[こうひょう]:official announcement/proclamation, 確約[かくやく]:firm promise/definite promise
（一郎）ああ
本社にも不具合の公表を確約させた
Yeah, I made the head office promise to announce the fault officially.
落ち度[おちど]:mistake/error/fault
カンナ君には
なんの落ち度もない
Kanna was not responsible for that.
誤解[ごかい]:misunderstanding, 一緒[いっしょ]:together|at the same time|same, 解く[とく]:to untie|to unsew|to solve||, 解く[ほどく]:to unfasten/to untie/to unwrap (e.g. parcel)
研一君
みんなの誤解を一緒に解こう
Ken'ichi,
let's resolve everyone's misunderstandings together.
は… はい
Y-Yes!
ハラケン よかった
（ハラケン）うん
Haraken, that's great.
Yes!
巻き込む[まきこむ]:to roll up/to enfold|to involve
天沢さんも… カンナを
自分が巻き込んだんじゃないかと
Amasawa was troubled by her belief that she was responsible for involving Kanna.
気に病む[きにやむ]:to worry/to fret (over something)/to be worried
気に病んでいたわ
大黒[だいこく]:god of wealth|monk's wife, 市[いち]:market/fair, 市[し]:city, 内[うち]:inside|while|among||, 内[ない]:inside/within
大黒市内に入るぞ
We're entering Daikoku City!
お兄さん[おにいさん]:older brother/elder brother|(vocative) young man
（ヤサコ）天沢さんのお兄さんが？
Amasawa's brother?!
亡くなる[なくなる]:to die, 交通事故[こうつうじこ]:traffic accident
（オバちゃん）そう
亡くなったのは交通事故よ
Yes.
He died in a car accident.
５年前のね
Five years ago.
I gotta tell Amasawa about this.
伝える[つたえる]:to convey/to report/to transmit
天沢さんに伝えないと…
ああっ…
（モジョ）モジョ！
Mojo!
持つ[もつ]:to hold (in one's hand)|to possess|to maintain||
んんっ… もう持たん！
I can't... hold out anymore!
なんじゃ？
Wha...
はじく:to flip/to snap|to repel
（猫目）これは なんだ？
なぜ はじかれる？
What is... this?
Why is it being repelled?
まさか:by no means/never!|something unexpected
まさか… タケル！
Don't tell me...
Takeru!
（ヤサコ）あっ タケル君
Takeru.
兄ちゃん[あんちゃん]:(my) older brother|sonny (with a nuance of suspicion)/lad, 兄ちゃん[にいちゃん]:familiar form of "older brother", ライン:line, 全て[すべて]:everything/all|entirely, はじく:to flip/to snap|to repel
（タケル）兄ちゃんのラインは
全て はじいたよ
I repelled all of my brother's attacks.
以上[いじょう]:not less than|beyond ... (e.g. one's means)|above-mentioned||
もうこれ以上
ヒドいことはしないで！
Don't do awful things anymore!
What are you talking about?
（猫目）何を言うんだ？
実験[じっけん]:experiment, データ:data/datum, 残る[のこる]:to remain/to be left, 父さん[とうさん]:father/dad/papa, 功績[こうせき]:achievements/merit/meritorious service, 世界[せかい]:the world|sphere|renowned|
この実験データが残れば
父さんの功績は世界に…
With this experimental data, we can demonstrate Dad's achievements to the world!
父ちゃん[とうちゃん, とっちゃん]:dad/daddy/papa, 喜ぶ[よろこぶ]:to be delighted|to congratulate|to gratefully accept
そんなの
父ちゃんが喜ぶわけがない
There's no way Dad would be happy about that!
父ちゃん[とうちゃん, とっちゃん]:dad/daddy/papa, イマーゴ:imago, 電脳[でんのう]:computer|cyberbrain/digital brain, ペット:pet, ペット:polyethylene terephthalate/PET
父ちゃんは
イマーゴや電脳ペットを…
Dad created Imago and cyberpets...
治す[なおす]:to cure|to fix|to do over again (after -masu base of verb)||, 作る[つくる]:to make|to prepare (food)|to raise||
人の心を治すために作ったんだ！
to heal people's minds!
タケル君
Takeru...
今まで[いままで]:until now/so far/up to the present, 黙る[だまる]:to be silent
ヤサコ 今まで黙っててごめん
Yasako,
I'm sorry I never told you.
やめる:to stop (an activity)/to cease|to cancel, やめる:to resign/to retire/to quit
（猫目）やめろ タケル！
Stop it,
Takeru!
何を… したの？
What
did you do?
兄ちゃん[あんちゃん]:(my) older brother|sonny (with a nuance of suspicion)/lad, 兄ちゃん[にいちゃん]:familiar form of "older brother", メガネ:spectacles/glasses, 壊す[こわす]:to break|to wreck|to break (a bill, etc.)
兄ちゃんのメガネを壊した
I broke my brother's glasses.
小さい[ちいさい]:small/little/tiny, 頃[ころ, ごろ]:(approximate) time|suitable time (or condition)|time of year, 頃[けい]:qing (Chinese unit of land area equal to 100 mu), 父ちゃん[とうちゃん, とっちゃん]:dad/daddy/papa, もらう:to receive/to take|to get somebody to do something, パスワード:(computer) password
小さい頃 父ちゃんからもらった
パスワードなんだ
It's a password Dad gave me when I was very little.
タケル君
Takeru...
More important than that, Yasako!
早い[はやい]:fast|early (in the day, etc.)|(too) soon|, 呼び戻す[よびもどす]:to call back/to call home
そんなことより ヤサコ
早く天沢を呼び戻すんだ！
You gotta call Isako back home!
Yeah!
だいぶ:lengthy (of a book, etc.)/voluminous|most (e.g. most part), だいぶ:considerably/greatly/a lot, ダメージ:damage, 受ける[うける, ウケる]:to receive|to catch (e.g. a ball)|to be struck by (wind, waves, sunlight, etc.)||, リンク:link/directory entry, 遠のく[とおのく]:to become distant/to recede
（メガばあ）
だいぶダメージを受けた
リンクが遠のいておる
She's taken quite a lot of damage.
The link is fading more and more.
What's the destination of this link?
リンク[リンク]:link/directory entry|rink, 先[さき]:previous|point (e.g. pencil)|head (of a line)||, コイル:coil, ドメイン:domain, 似る[にる]:to resemble/to look like|to be similar (in status, condition, etc.)
なんなの？　このリンク先
コイルドメインに似てるけど
It looks like the Coil Domain, but...
I guess it's a mental Space just like "the other side."
恐らく[おそらく]:perhaps/likely/probably, あっち:that way (direction distant from both speaker and listener)/over there|that one (something physically distant from both speaker and listener, or something not visible but known by both speaker and listener), 同じ[おなじ, おんなじ]:same/identical|(usu. part of a 'nara' conditional) anyway, 種類[しゅるい]:variety/kind|counter for different sorts of things, 精神[せいしん]:mind/soul/heart, 空間[くうかん]:space/room/airspace, 空間[あきま]:vacancy/room for rent or lease
（メガばあ）恐らく あっちと
同じ種類の精神空間じゃろう
今まで[いままで]:until now/so far/up to the present, 空間[くうかん]:space/room/airspace, 空間[あきま]:vacancy/room for rent or lease
しかし 今までいた空間とも違う
But it's different from the Space where she's been till now.
正体[しょうたい]:true character/true form|consciousness, 修復[しゅうふく, しゅふく]:restoration/repair/mending
（オバちゃん）
正体が分からなくては
修復できないわ
If we don't understand its nature, we can't repair it!
さっき:some time ago/just now, さっき:thirst for blood/bloodlust/determination to kill, リンク:link/directory entry, つながり:connection/link/relationship, かける:to hang (e.g. picture)/to hoist (e.g. sail)|to sit, かける:to run (race, esp. horse)/to dash|to gallop (one's horse)
（メガばあ）
さっき リンクがつながりかけて
Just as the link made the connection,
急[きゅう]:urgent|sharp|rapid||, 苦しい[くるしい]:painful|needy|forced (smile, joke)||, 顔[かお, がん]:face|look|honor|, 顔[かんばせ]:countenance/visage|face
急に苦しそうな顔になったのじゃ
she got a pained expression.
苦しい[くるしい]:painful|needy|forced (smile, joke)||, 顔[かお, がん]:face|look|honor|, 顔[かんばせ]:countenance/visage|face
苦しそうな顔？
A pained... expression?
痛み[いたみ]:pain/ache|damage
痛み…
Pain...
こっち… こっちよ 天沢さん！
Here...
Come here, Amasawa!
声[こえ]:voice
私の声を聞いて！
Listen to my voice!
天沢さん こっちを見て！
Amasawa!
Look here!
天沢さん！
ううっ…
（ハラケン）ヤサコ！
Yasako!
夢[ゆめ]:dream
これ 夢の…
This
was in my dream.
夕焼け[ゆうやけ]:evening glow/red sunset/afterglow (of sunset)
夕焼け？
The evening gloom!
Yasako!
ヤサコ！
分離[ぶんり]:separation/partition/detachment
これは分離ではない
She hasn't shifted.
リンク[リンク]:link/directory entry|rink, 先[さき]:previous|point (e.g. pencil)|head (of a line)||, 内側[うちがわ, ないそく]:inside/interior/inner part
リンク先は… 内側？
The link's destination is...
inside?
接続[せつぞく]:connection|changing trains|conjunction
（信彦）どうやって接続したの？
How did you connect here?
特別[とくべつ]:special, 子供[こども]:child/children, 入れる[いれる]:to put in|to admit|to accept||
ここには
特別な子供しか入れないんだよ
Only special kids can enter here.
（ヤサコ）ここは どこなの？
What is this place?
This is a Space created for a certain girl.
女の子[おんなのこ, おんなのコ]:girl/daughter|young woman, 女の子[めのこ]:woman/girl, 作る[つくる]:to make|to prepare (food)|to raise||, 空間[くうかん]:space/room/airspace, 空間[あきま]:vacancy/room for rent or lease
（信彦）ある女の子のために
作られた空間なんだ
傷[きず, キズ]:wound|chip|flaw||, 癒える[いえる]:to recover/to be healed, 子供[こども]:child/children, 場所[ばしょ]:place|room|basho
傷が癒えるまで いつまでも
子供のままでいられる場所
A place where she can continue to be a child until she's healed.
空間[くうかん]:space/room/airspace, 空間[あきま]:vacancy/room for rent or lease, 一緒[いっしょ]:together|at the same time|same
僕は もうすぐいなくなるんだ
この空間と一緒にね
You know, I'm gonna be leaving soon.
Together with this Space.
いなくなるって？
Leaving?
女の子[おんなのこ, おんなのコ]:girl/daughter|young woman, 女の子[めのこ]:woman/girl, 借りる[かりる]:to borrow/to have a loan|to rent, いける:to arrange (flowers)/to plant|living, いける:to be good (at)/to go well|to look (taste, etc.) good
（信彦）その女の子は
もう僕の力を借りてはいけないんだ
That girl
can't rely on my strength anymore.
決まり[きまり]:rule|settlement|habit||
そういう決まりなんだ
It's the rule.
My role will soon be over.
役目[やくめ]:duty/role/function, 終わる[おわる]:to finish/to end/to close
僕の役目は もうすぐ終わる
（鳴き声）
（ヤサコ）デンスケ！
Densuke!
（信彦）ヤサコ
Yasako.
犬[いぬ, イヌ]:dog (Canis (lupus) familiaris)|snoop (i.e. a detective, a spy, etc.)|loser|
（信彦）この犬のあとを
ついてきたんだね
So you arrived here by following this dog, huh?
どうり:reason/logic/sense
どうりで…
It means that...
（ヤサコ）４４２３は
ここで何をしてるの？
What are you doing here, 4-4-2-3?
女の子[おんなのこ, おんなのコ]:girl/daughter|young woman, 女の子[めのこ]:woman/girl, 治療[ちりょう, じりょう]:medical treatment/cure
（信彦）僕は その女の子の
治療をしているんだ
I'm healing that girl.
心のね
Healing her heart.
医者[いしゃ]:(medical) doctor/physician
（ヤサコ）お医者さんなの？
Are you a doctor?
（信彦）ああ そうだね
Yeah, you could say that.
イマーゴ:imago
君はイマーゴがあるんだね
So you have the Imago.
Then, you'd better go home now.
帰る[かえる]:to return|to leave|to get home
なら もう帰ったほうがいい
空間[くうかん]:space/room/airspace, 空間[あきま]:vacancy/room for rent or lease, 反応[はんのう, はんおう]:reaction/response, しまう:to finish/to stop|to close (a business, etc.)
この空間は
君のような子に反応してしまう
This Space reacts to kids like you.
逃げる[にげる]:to escape/to run away
（ヤサコ）逃げて ２人とも！
Run!
Both of you!
やめる:to stop (an activity)/to cease|to cancel, やめる:to resign/to retire/to quit, お兄ちゃん[おにいちゃん]:familiar form of "older brother"|form of address for young adult male/mister, 取る[とる]:to take|to steal|to eat||
（ミチコ）
やめて！　お兄ちゃんを取らないで
Stop!
Don't steal my brother!
あなたが…
あなたがミチコさんなのね
You are...
You're Miss Michiko, aren't you?!
マズい:unappetising|unskillful|ugly|, 生み出す[うみだす]:to create|to invent|to give birth to, しまう:to finish/to stop|to close (a business, etc.)
マズい… もう１人
生み出してしまったのか
This is very bad.
Another one has been born!
早い[はやい]:fast|early (in the day, etc.)|(too) soon|, 逃げる[にげる]:to escape/to run away
早く逃げるんだ ヤサコ！
Run, quickly! Yasako!
やめる:to stop (an activity)/to cease|to cancel, やめる:to resign/to retire/to quit
（幼少のイサコ）やめて！
Stop it!
お兄ちゃん[おにいちゃん]:familiar form of "older brother"|form of address for young adult male/mister, 別れる[わかれる]:to part (usu. of people)|to separate (of a couple)|to lose (e.g. one's mother)
お兄ちゃんと別れたくない！
I don't want to be separated from my brother!
I'll be with my brother forever!
お兄ちゃん[おにいちゃん]:familiar form of "older brother"|form of address for young adult male/mister, ずっと:continuously in some state (for a long time, distance)/throughout|much (better, etc.), 一緒[いっしょ]:together|at the same time|same
私はお兄ちゃんと
ずっと一緒にいるの！
違う！
That's not true!
お兄ちゃん[おにいちゃん]:familiar form of "older brother"|form of address for young adult male/mister, さよなら:good-bye
私はお兄ちゃんと
さよならをしたの！
I'd already said goodbye to my brother!
Amasawa,
天沢さん そこにいるのね？
you're there, aren't you?!
I understand...
分かった… 分かったの！
I understand now!
小此木…
Okonogi?
Listen.
願う[ねがう]:to desire|to beg|to have something done for oneself
聞いて！
天沢さんがミチコさんに願う前に
Before you made that wish to Miss Michiko,
your brother was already dead, Amasawa.
お兄さん[おにいさん]:older brother/elder brother|(vocative) young man
お兄さんは死んでいたの
You didn't make your brother die!
お兄さん[おにいさん]:older brother/elder brother|(vocative) young man
お兄さんを死なせたのは
あなたじゃない
The one who's there with you is...
そこにいるのは…
No.
お兄ちゃん[おにいちゃん]:familiar form of "older brother"|form of address for young adult male/mister, ずっと:continuously in some state (for a long time, distance)/throughout|much (better, etc.)
（ミチコ）ダメ…
お兄ちゃんは ずっと私のものなの
My brother will always be mine!
I hate you!
なんか:things like .../or something like that ... (often derogatory), なんか:something, 嫌い[きらい]:dislike|suspicion|distinction, 嫌い[ぎらい]:dislike/hatred/fear
あんたなんか嫌い！
I understand now.
分かったの
You didn't give birth to Miss Michiko by yourself.
一人[ひとり, いちにん]:one person|alone/unmarried, 生み出す[うみだす]:to create|to invent|to give birth to
ミチコさんは天沢さん一人が
生み出したんじゃない
No!
イヤ！
Another person
生み出す[うみだす]:to create|to invent|to give birth to
（ヤサコ）もう１人いたの
ミチコさんを生み出した人が
helped you give birth to Miss Michiko.
And that person was...
それは…
Stop it!
やめる:to stop (an activity)/to cease|to cancel, やめる:to resign/to retire/to quit
やめて！
Me,
この私 小此木優子よ！
Yuko Okonogi!
My kiss interfered with your goodbyes.
別れ[わかれ]:parting/separation/farewell, 邪魔[じゃま]:hindrance|to visit (somebody's home)|demon who hinders Buddhist training, しまう:to finish/to stop|to close (a business, etc.)
（ヤサコ）
私のキスが あなたたちの別れを
邪魔してしまった
Michiko was born from my kiss and your anguish.
苦しみ[くるしみ]:pain/anguish/distress, 子供[こども]:child/children
ミチコは私のキスと
あなたの苦しみの子供
Amasawa,
戻ってくる[もどってくる]:to come back
天沢さん 戻ってくるのよ
you gotta come back.
You should've left this Space already!
空間[くうかん]:space/room/airspace, 空間[あきま]:vacancy/room for rent or lease, さよなら:good-bye
もう その空間とは
さよならをしたはずなんだから！
I won't allow it.
許す[ゆるす]:to permit|to exempt (from fine)|to confide in|
（ミチコ）そんなの許さない！
Run!
走る[はしる]:to run|to travel (movement of vehicles)|to hurry to||
走って！
The link... is coming back!
リンク:link/directory entry, 戻ってくる[もどってくる]:to come back
（オバちゃん）
リンクが戻ってくるわ
Amasawa!
天沢さん！　そうよ こっちよ
Right,
this way!
Can you really abandon me like this?
捨てる[すてる]:to throw away|to abandon|to give up
（ミチコ）あなたは
本当に私を捨てられる？
It's not what you wish.
望む[のぞむ]:to desire|to wish for|to see
あなたは それを望んでない
Amasawa!
天沢さん！
You definitely can't part from me.
離れる[はなれる]:to be separated|to leave|to leave (a job, etc.)|, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation
（ミチコ）
私と離れることなんてできない
You're the one who gave birth to me.
生み出す[うみだす]:to create|to invent|to give birth to
私を生み出したのはあなた
I'm the child you made to eat your anguish and sadness.
苦しみ[くるしみ]:pain/anguish/distress, 悲しみ[かなしみ]:sadness/sorrow|affection, 食べる[たべる]:to eat|to live on (e.g. a salary)/to live off, 生み出す[うみだす]:to create|to invent|to give birth to
私はあなたの苦しみを 悲しみを
食べるために生み出した―
分身[ぶんしん]:parturition/delivery/one's child
あなたの分身
It doesn't matter how many times you kill me,
何度[なんど]:how many times?/how often?, よみがえる:to be resurrected/to be resuscitated|to be recalled (e.g. memories)
何度 殺しても
私は何度でもよみがえる
I'll always be born again!
Because I'm your true soul.
本心[ほんしん]:true feelings
だって 私は
あなたの本心なのだから
Stop! Stop already!
やめる:to stop (an activity)/to cease|to cancel, やめる:to resign/to retire/to quit
やめて… もうやめて！
You wanted to throw away your feelings for your brother,
お兄さん[おにいさん]:older brother/elder brother|(vocative) young man, 思い[おもい]:thought|imagination|desire||, 捨てる[すてる]:to throw away|to abandon|to give up, 勝手に[かってに]:arbitrarily/of its own accord/voluntarily, 大人[おとな, だいにん]:adult, 大人[たいじん]:man of substance or virtue|giant|adult
（ミチコ）
あなたはお兄さんへの思いを捨てて
勝手に大人になろうとした
and become an adult without me.
I won't allow that.
許す[ゆるす]:to permit|to exempt (from fine)|to confide in|
そんなの私が許さない
天沢さん！
Amasawa!
ヤサコ！
Yasako!
戻る[もどる]:to turn back (e.g. half-way)|to return|to recover (e.g. something lost)|, 戻る[もとる]:to go against/to act contrary to/to deviate from, なさる:to do
（ミチコ）さあ 戻ってきなさい
Come on, come back.
とても:very/awfully|(not) at all, 心地[ここち]:feeling/sensation|sensation of doing (usu. after -masu stem of verb), 心地[しんじ]:padding/lining/foundation
こっちは とても心地いいわ
This place feels so good.
お兄さん[おにいさん]:older brother/elder brother|(vocative) young man, 大人[おとな, だいにん]:adult, 大人[たいじん]:man of substance or virtue|giant|adult, 必要[ひつよう]:necessary/needed|necessity
お兄さんも ここにいる
ここでは大人になる必要はない
Your brother is also here.
You don't need to become an adult here.
You can keep your sweet and lonely feelings for all time.
甘い[あまい]:sweet-tasting|fragrant (smelling)|lightly salted||, 甘い[うまい]:skillful|delicious|fortunate, 切ない[せつない]:painful/heartrending|oppressive, 気持ち[きもち]:feeling|preparedness|thanks|
いつまでも
甘くて切ない気持ちでいられる
ずっと:continuously in some state (for a long time, distance)/throughout|much (better, etc.), 子供[こども]:child/children
ずっと子供のままでいていいのよ
You can be a child forever.
勇子…
Yuko.
いける:to arrange (flowers)/to plant|living, いける:to be good (at)/to go well|to look (taste, etc.) good
いけない ダメ！
It's no good...
No!
そっちへ行ってはダメ！
天沢さん！
You don't have to go there!
Amasawa!
髪の毛[かみのけ]:hair (head), 結ぶ[むすぶ]:to tie|to bear (fruit)|to close (e.g. deal)||
（幼少のイサコ）髪の毛 結んで
Tie my hair!
天沢さん… うっ！
Amasawa...
やめる:to stop (an activity)/to cease|to cancel, やめる:to resign/to retire/to quit
ヤサコ もうやめて！
Yasako, stop now!
待って！
Wait!
以上[いじょう]:not less than|beyond ... (e.g. one's means)|above-mentioned||, 危険[きけん]:danger/peril|risk, 止める[とめる]:to stop|to park|to prevent||, 止める[やめる]:to stop (an activity)/to cease|to cancel
これ以上は危険じゃ！
（オバちゃん）止めるぞ
Beyond this point, it's dangerous!
We gotta stop her.
ダメだ！
（オバちゃん）ハッ…
No!
任せる[まかせる]:to entrust (e.g. a task) to another|to passively leave to someone else's facilities|to leave to take its natural course||
ヤサコに任せるんだ
Let Yasako do it.
（ミチコ）
ここにいれば なんにもいらない
In this place,
you don't need anything.
大人[おとな, だいにん]:adult, 大人[たいじん]:man of substance or virtue|giant|adult, 痛み[いたみ]:pain/ache|damage, 苦しみ[くるしみ]:pain/anguish/distress
大人になるための
痛みも苦しみも…
Neither the pain, nor the anguish
of becoming an adult.
天沢さんのバカ！
Stupid Amasawa...
それでも天沢勇子なの？
Do you deserve the name of Yuko Amasawa?
勇ましい[いさましい]:brave/valiant|stirring, 戻る[もどる]:to turn back (e.g. half-way)|to return|to recover (e.g. something lost)|, 戻る[もとる]:to go against/to act contrary to/to deviate from
あの勇ましい天沢さんなら
戻ってこられるはずよ！
That courageous Amasawa
would be able to come back.
勇ましい[いさましい]:brave/valiant|stirring
勇子のユウは…
勇ましいのユウ！
The "Yu" in Yuko is
the one from "courageous"!
やめる:to stop (an activity)/to cease|to cancel, やめる:to resign/to retire/to quit
やめて
Stop it!
痛い[いたい]:painful/sore|exceeding
痛い…
It hurts.
勇ましい[いさましい]:brave/valiant|stirring
勇ましい…
You're courageous...
痛み[いたみ]:pain/ache|damage, 恐れる[おそれる]:to fear/to be afraid of, 勇ましい[いさましい]:brave/valiant|stirring, 女の子[おんなのこ, おんなのコ]:girl/daughter|young woman, 女の子[めのこ]:woman/girl
あなたは痛みを恐れない
勇ましい女の子
You don't fear the pain.
You're a "courageous girl."
だから イサコ！
So Isako...
戻る[もどる]:to turn back (e.g. half-way)|to return|to recover (e.g. something lost)|, 戻る[もとる]:to go against/to act contrary to/to deviate from, なさる:to do
戻ってきなさい！　イサコ！
come back!
Isako!
ヤサコ？
Yasako...
ダメ ダメよ！
No! No!
わあっ…
やめる:to stop (an activity)/to cease|to cancel, やめる:to resign/to retire/to quit
やめて 何をするの？
Stop!
What are you doing?
行くんだ 勇子！
Go, Yuko!
お兄ちゃん[おにいちゃん]:familiar form of "older brother"|form of address for young adult male/mister
お兄ちゃん
Brother...
さよなら:good-bye
これで 本当のさよならだ
This is
our true goodbye.
（ミチコ）待って 行ってはダメ…
Wait...
You don't have to go.
That way, there's nothing but pain and anguish!
痛み[いたみ]:pain/ache|damage, 苦しみ[くるしみ]:pain/anguish/distress
そっちには
痛みと苦しみしかないの
（イサコ）だから…
That's why...
だから行かなければならないの
That's why I have to go.
私は これから
あなたたちなしでも―
Because from now on,
I have to carry on living
一人[ひとり, いちにん]:one person|alone/unmarried, 生きる[いきる]:to live|to make a living|to be in effect||
自分一人で
生きていかなくてはならないから
by myself without you.
やめる:to stop (an activity)/to cease|to cancel, やめる:to resign/to retire/to quit
（ミチコ）やめて 私の勇子
Wait, my Yuko.
Don't abandon me, Yuko.
捨てる[すてる]:to throw away|to abandon|to give up
私を捨てないで 勇子！
生きる[いきる]:to live|to make a living|to be in effect||, なさる:to do
（ヤサコ）生きなさい 勇子
Go, Yuko!
痛み[いたみ]:pain/ache|damage, 感じる[かんじる]:to feel/to sense/to experience, 方向[ほうこう]:direction/orientation|course (e.g. of action), 出口[でぐち]:exit/gateway/way out
（ヤサコ･イサコ）
痛みを感じる方向に出口がある！
In the direction where you feel the pain, there's an exit!
夢[ゆめ]:dream, つながる:to be tied together/to be connected to|to lead to
（イサコ）
あなたの夢につながっていたのね
So it was connected to your dream.
不思議[ふしぎ]:wonder/miracle/strange
（ヤサコ）うん
いつも不思議に思ってた
Yup,
I always thought it was mysterious.
世界[せかい]:the world|sphere|renowned|
私の心の世界は
The world inside my heart...
ずっと:continuously in some state (for a long time, distance)/throughout|much (better, etc.), 世界[せかい]:the world|sphere|renowned|, つながる:to be tied together/to be connected to|to lead to
ずっと あなたの心の世界に
つながってた
has always been connected to the world inside your heart.
I did
嫌い[きらい]:dislike|suspicion|distinction, 嫌い[ぎらい]:dislike/hatred/fear
私 あなたのことが嫌いだった
hate you.
嫌い[きらい]:dislike|suspicion|distinction, 嫌い[ぎらい]:dislike/hatred/fear
でも分かったの
なぜ嫌いだったのか
But now I know.
I know why I hated you.
ずっと:continuously in some state (for a long time, distance)/throughout|much (better, etc.), 怖い[こわい]:scary/frightening|(I'm) afraid
ずっと怖かった
I was afraid.
つながる:to be tied together/to be connected to|to lead to, 怖い[こわい]:scary/frightening|(I'm) afraid
誰かと心がつながることが
怖かった
I was afraid to open my heart to someone.
But I'm not afraid anymore.
怖い[こわい]:scary/frightening|(I'm) afraid
でも もう怖くない
見失う[みうしなう]:to lose sight of/to miss, 必ず[かならず]:always/without exception/necessarily, 道[みち]:road|distance|the way (of proper conduct, etc.)||, 道[どう]:road|way|Buddhist teachings||
見失っても
必ず道は どこかにある
Even if I lose sight of it,
there's always a path somewhere.
細い[ほそい]:thin/slender|unlucky (billiards slang), 細い[こまい]:small/fine|stingy, 道[みち]:road|distance|the way (of proper conduct, etc.)||, 道[どう]:road|way|Buddhist teachings||, つながる:to be tied together/to be connected to|to lead to
人は細い道でつながってる
People are connected through narrow paths.
時々[ときどき]:sometimes/at times, 見失う[みうしなう]:to lose sight of/to miss
時々 見失うけど
Even if sometimes they lose sight of them...
きっと:surely/undoubtedly|sternly, つながる:to be tied together/to be connected to|to lead to
でも きっと つながっている
There's no doubt they're connected.
おかえり:return|welcome home
おかえり イサコ
Welcome back, Isako.
ただいま:Here I am/I'm home!|presently
ただいま ヤサコ
I'm back, Yasako.
kono michi wo susunda nara
If I follow this path,
itsuka mata kimi ni
perhaps I'll meet you
We failed our last independent research project in elementary school.
小学生[しょうがくせい]:elementary school student/primary school student/grade school student, 最後[さいご]:last|no sooner than|one's final moments, 自由[じゆう]:freedom/liberty/as it pleases you, 研究[けんきゅう]:study/research/investigation
（ハラケン）
小学生 最後の自由研究
損なう[そこなう]:to harm/to hurt|to fail to ...
やり損なっちゃった
aeru darou
again someday.
Yeah, you're right.
（ヤサコ）あっ そうね
That's why I decided to stop right now.
終わる[おわる]:to finish/to end/to close, ことにする:to make a distinction/to differ/to be different, ことにする:to decide to|to pretend that
（ハラケン）
だから 今 終わらせることにした
tooku tsuzuite iku toki no naka de
When I continue into the distance,
The research on Illegals.
イリーガル:illegal, 研究[けんきゅう]:study/research/investigation
イリーガルの研究
I wonder what Illegals really were?
イリーガル:illegal
（ハラケン）イリーガルって
なんだったんだろう？
kyou wo natsukashimu
I'll surely long
I always wondered about that...
ずっと:continuously in some state (for a long time, distance)/throughout|much (better, etc.), 考える[かんがえる]:to think about|to ponder|to intend||
ずっと考えてた
kitto kono bashyo de
for this place.
今まで[いままで]:until now/so far/up to the present, イリーガル:illegal, 全部[ぜんぶ]:all/entire/whole
今までの
イリーガルは 全部
Whether maybe Illegals
were some sort of feeling.
感情[かんじょう]:emotion/feeling/feelings
何かの感情だったんじゃ
ないかって
kasuka ni mieru
I see them faintly
Like desire, or fear.
憧れ[あこがれ]:yearning/longing/aspiration, 怖い[こわい]:scary/frightening|(I'm) afraid
憧れとか 怖いとか
sora no kakera wo
and chase
会[え]:gathering (esp. Buddhist, festive, etc.), 会[かい]:meeting/assembly|association, しまう:to finish/to stop|to close (a business, etc.)
もう会えなくなって
しまった誰かに―
Like when you wish to meet...
oi kake de
the sky's fragments.
会いたいとか
someone who has passed away.
気持ち[きもち]:feeling|preparedness|thanks|
そういう気持ちを
誰にも知られずに―
I wonder if Illegals
hikari to kage mo
Light and shadow
are nothing more than Nulls
消える[きえる]:to go out/to vanish/to disappear, 気持ち[きもち]:feeling|preparedness|thanks|
消えていくはずの
気持ちを
拾い上げる[ひろいあげる]:to pick up/to pick out, たとする:to appreciate/to be thankful
あのヌルたちが
拾い上げていたとしたら
who picked up the various kinds of feelings
kokoro ni egaite
paint your heart
イリーガル:illegal
それがイリーガル
なんじゃないかって
that should've disappeared
without anyone knowing about them.
hashiru toki
when you run.
Maybe Kanna as well.
もしかし:perhaps/maybe/by some chance
もしかして カンナちゃんも？
sono waratta kao ga yuuki wo kureru
Your smiling face
Yup.
うん 僕の心の中のカンナが
Maybe the Kanna inside my heart
came to find me by following the path of my heart.
道[みち]:road|distance|the way (of proper conduct, etc.)||, 道[どう]:road|way|Buddhist teachings||, 通ずる[つうずる]:to be open (to traffic)|to flow (liquid, current)|to be understood||
心の道を通じて
会いにきたのかなって
nanigenai kotoba dake de
fills me with courage.
And if
イリーガル:illegal, たとする:to appreciate/to be thankful
もし ミチコさんも
イリーガルだったとしたら
Miss Michiko was also an Illegal,
kimi ga namida no hi wa
With just your careless words,
what could she have been...
なんだったんだろう？
tonde iku kara
you'll fly away
The feelings from when Amasawa and I gave birth to Miss Michiko.
生む[うむ]:to give birth/to bear (child)|to produce
私と天沢さんが
ミチコさんを生んだ―
itsudemo
on tearful days.
気持ち[きもち]:feeling|preparedness|thanks|
あのときの気持ち
donna toki mo
At any time, at any moment...
Lonely, sad...
切ない[せつない]:painful/heartrending|oppressive, 悲しい[かなしい]:sad/sorrowful
切なくて悲しくて それに…
and...
michi wa tsuzuiteru
And the path goes on...
A bit painful.
苦しい[くるしい]:painful|needy|forced (smile, joke)||
ちょっと苦しい
I wonder if those feelings might be...
気持ち[きもち]:feeling|preparedness|thanks|, もしかし:perhaps/maybe/by some chance
その気持ちって もしかして…
first love?
初恋[はつこい]:first love/puppy love
初恋かな？
（ヤサコ）えっ？
しれる:to become known/to come to light|to be known
（ヤサコ）うん
そうかもしれないわね
That could be the case.
The Next Spring
We became middle school students.
私たち[わたしたち, わたくしたち]:we/us, 中学生[ちゅうがくせい]:junior high school student/middle school pupil
私たちは
中学生になりました
In the end, Amasawa moved back to Kanazawa without saying anything.
結局[けっきょく]:after all|conclusion|ending of a game of Go
天沢さんは
結局 何も言わずに
しまう:to finish/to stop|to close (a business, etc.)
金沢(かなざわ)に
行ってしまいました
Yes, hello?
もしもし:hello (e.g. on phone)|excuse me! (when calling out to someone)
はい もしもし？
Amasawa?
天沢さん？
You know, I still don't know...
どっち:which way/which direction|which one (esp. of two alternatives)
ねえ 私まだ
どっちだか分からないの
Did we
私たち[わたしたち, わたくしたち]:we/us, 友達[ともだち]:friend/companion
私たちって
友達になれたのかな？
become friends... or not?
I already told you.
（イサコ）言っただろ
I don't really know what it means "to be friends."
友達[ともだち]:friend/companion
私は友達というものは
よく分からないんだ
Ah...
（ヤサコ）そう
But you...
（イサコ）
でも お前は そうだな…
Yup, you were a companion who got lost on the same path as me,
同じ[おなじ, おんなじ]:same/identical|(usu. part of a 'nara' conditional) anyway, 道[みち]:road|distance|the way (of proper conduct, etc.)||, 道[どう]:road|way|Buddhist teachings||, 迷う[まよう]:to lose one's way|to waver|to give into temptation|, 目指す[めざす]:to aim at/to have an eye on|to go toward
同じ道を迷って
同じ道を目指した仲間だ
and you looked for the same path I did.
But we're companions only when we're looking for the same path.
同じ[おなじ, おんなじ]:same/identical|(usu. part of a 'nara' conditional) anyway, 道[みち]:road|distance|the way (of proper conduct, etc.)||, 道[どう]:road|way|Buddhist teachings||, 目指す[めざす]:to aim at/to have an eye on|to go toward
（イサコ）でも仲間なのは
同じ道を目指してるときだけだ
A person like me, if I always stay with other people,
みたい:-like/sort of/similar to, 他人[たにん, ひと]:another person|unrelated person (i.e. not related by blood)|outsider, 一緒[いっしょ]:together|at the same time|same
私みたいな人間は
いつまでも他人と一緒にいては
I lose sight of my own path.
道[みち]:road|distance|the way (of proper conduct, etc.)||, 道[どう]:road|way|Buddhist teachings||, 見える[みえる]:to be seen|to look|to come, 見える[まみえる]:to have an audience|to face (an enemy)|to serve (esp. as one's wife), しまう:to finish/to stop|to close (a business, etc.)
自分の道が見えなくなってしまう
Maybe you're right.
（ヤサコ）そうかもね
Let's meet again.
同じ[おなじ, おんなじ]:same/identical|(usu. part of a 'nara' conditional) anyway, 道[みち]:road|distance|the way (of proper conduct, etc.)||, 道[どう]:road|way|Buddhist teachings||, 迷う[まよう]:to lose one's way|to waver|to give into temptation|
また会おう 同じ道を迷ったときに
When we get lost again.
Yes.
Until that time,
さよなら:good-bye
それまでは さよならだ
goodbye.
Yes.
I'm Isako.
私はイサコ
You're the one who gave me my name.
名付け親[なづけおや]:godparent|first person to give something its name
名付け親は あんただ
（京子(きょうこ)）んっ？
Densuke...
デンスケ？
Kyoko, did you see him?
見える[みえる]:to be seen|to look|to come, 見える[まみえる]:to have an audience|to face (an enemy)|to serve (esp. as one's wife)
京子 見えた？